[Music]
in a case report of the successful
management of type 2 diabetes with a
lifestyle intervention a 45 year old
fellow took responsibility for health
into his own hands and sought to defeat
his disease and get off the drugs by
eating foods purported to be
anti-diabetic
but how strong is the evidence for let's
say ginger
diabetes is reaching pandemic levels and
requires safe affordable and effective
therapies so what about the potential of
ginger in the prevention and treatment
well
in a
petri dish
increasing exposure to ginger compounds
improves blood sugar uptake of muscle
cells almost as much as the popular
diabetes drug metformin and in rats
ginger might work even better than
metformin
but weight and blood sugar reduction
observed in rodent models does not
necessarily translate to humans
in this study a combination of
nutraceuticals caused mice to lose 30 of
their body weight in one month but in
people
no
benefit compared to placebo you don't
know if something works in humans
until you put it to the test
if you feed people refine flour white
bread with a cup of water this is what
happens to the blood sugars over the
next two hours
but drink some unsweetened green tea
with that white bread instead and
there's less of a blood sugar spike same
with cinnamon tea and
same with ginger tea made by mixing a
tablespoon of grated fresh ginger in a
cup of hot water
okay but these were healthy normal
subjects what about the effects of
ginger
in diabetics
this was the first study of its kind
diabetics randomized to take a teaspoon
of ground ginger a day for two months
hidden in pill form so they could
compare it with identical looking sugar
pill placebos and
ginger supplementation decreased the
levels of insulin which is a good thing
and lower triglycerides and ldl
cholesterol but without a significant
effect on blood sugars now look heart
disease is the leading killer of
diabetics so a 13 drop in ldl bad
cholesterol would be reason enough to
shell out the nickel a day would cost to
add that much ginger to your diet
but would have been nice to see an
improvement in blood sugar control i
mean there was that drop in insulin
levels which suggests improved insulin
sensitivity and indeed there was a
significant drop in insulin resistance
so maybe they just didn't give ginger
long enough time to work well that way
that was two months how about
three months
even less ginger just 1.6 grams less
than a teaspoon a day but for 12 weeks
and
maybe ginger can reduce blood sugars
after all and decrease inflammation
cutting c-reactive protein levels in
half
okay what about going back to just eight
weeks but this time using a higher dose
three grams a day or about one and a
half teaspoons and
a
significant decrease in fasting blood
sugars and long-term blood sugar control
in the ginger group thereby showing the
effect of ginger in controlling diabetes
check it out the placebo group continued
to get worse the ginger group got better
similarly amazing randomized double
blind placebo control results for a
teaspoon a day for 12 weeks and for a
teaspoon and a half all better in the
ginger group all worse in the non-ginger
group all significantly different
just because of a little cheap safe
simple side effect free spice
put all the studies together and they
clearly demonstrate that ginger can
lower blood sugar levels and improve
long-term blood sugar control and at a
totally manageable dose i mean you could
just dump a teaspoon of ginger powder in
a cup of hot water and just drink it
down
so
overall adding a little spice to our
life may serve as a delicious and
sensible way to maintain a healthy body
[Music]
you